This is a question that really touches
me personally
because as I become more involved in
veganism and become more interested in
animal rights,
it's really been difficult for me to
retain the same amount of compassion for other
humans, especially other humans that are hurting animals, as I fo for
other animals so what is the best way to
retain compassion for non-vegans
while still promoting veganism?
My diet is what you would call vegan,
but I don't really say
often anymore, "I am a vegan" I'll say
that I don't eat animal products but
identifying
with any kind of label that excludes
others ends up being the basis for
limiting where our compassion extends and then the basis for conflict.
And so we want to not just be
Americans or you know,
Christians or whatever limited group.
We want to be citizens of the planet. And we
want to be not just human
citizens but earthlings, we want to
continue to expand our sense of
connectedness to the rest of life
and so I think there's even an identity
level of I am
a vegan or an animal activist as opposed to just, compassion is a deep value for
me.
Everybody actually values compassion
even if their circle hasn't extended as
far yet. They value it towards their kids,
towards
their pets usually, towards some
things. And then we identify again what's
the same between us not what's different
and then we get to have a basis for
building from there
because with the exception of a few
people that were raised by very
conscious parents in this way,
most about us ate meat while experiencing ourself as ethical, caring, loving people.
I did, right, and so the me today could
easily be judging the previous me as uncaring
and I wasn't uncaring, I was unaware.
And awareness requires more than just
hearing,
"Oh, animals suffer somewhere, it requires
actually getting it to change a lifelong
pattern that our whole family has done, our
whole culture has done,
almost everybody around us has done
since we were a baby. And so we're
looking at changing something profound, we're looking at changing
how someone supports their own life,
staying alive at like a multiple times
a day basis,
which is why the act to of becoming vegetarian is such a huge one,
because when you say, "Hey the way that I support my staying alive and something
that I do every day, multiple times and
something I've done since
since I was an infant, I'm gonna change that", it's a huge chance.
And if you're changing it not just for
you, if you change for health reasons
it's different
because they you learn another health fad and it just keeps changing but if you change
a core way of how you support your life, that started
early on and everyone around you is
still doing the other thing,
for the purpose of compassion,
then you're saying that compassion is
actually one of my core values and I'm
actually going to guide
the core aspects of my life by that
value and that ends up
bleeding over into so many other areas.
You start recognizing, oh my purchases
affect things in ways I they don't see. If I had to go to the factory farm to buy meat,
I would never get the meat but because the atrocity is somewhere else I don't notice
it.
What about landfills? Isn't it like that
too? And now I'm gonna start being conscientious
about my waste.
What about, did may did my shoes
come from a place that was
a using child slave labor? Was
animal testing involved in my cosmetics?
And you start really taking responsibility
for
the effects that are invisible to us if
we don't dig but that are very real
in the matter to somebody else. And that
active saying
compassion and responsibility for that
compassion come together as the core of
my life.
That I'm actually not just going have
compassion where I care but I don't do
anything about it, but
I'm going have compassion and I'm going to act on it
and that becomes a central defining
thing about who I am. That's such an
essential shift.
And it's my belief that
everybody wants to have their life be a
positive impact on others' lives,
as they get more informed and they get
more sensitized and that those who are
capable of causing more harm, whether it's to animals or anything,
is both because of a lack of awareness, a lack of resources for other
opportunities and because of their own
hurts and wounds that have shut their
empathy down.
And so it's really a process at helping
people to re-sensitize
and to have new resources and strategies and have deeper awareness
which means that going to attack them is the exact opposite of what would help.
Recognizing our sameness with
them recognizing the goodness
that's
that's there and then helping to both
healing offer new strategies is what
relevant.
I think that's a great point to close on and
I really appreciate you being with me
today.
I really look forward to delving deeper
into these topics with you
and learning more about veganism. Thanks Michelle, I'm really
excited about your blog
and that you're sharing this with people.